Guide to the Charles H. Snow Collection on NYU During World War I MC 25
New York University Archives
Charles H. Snow Collection on NYU During World War I
Bulk, 1933-1943
1917-1943
MC 25
New York University Archives
1.25 linear feet
The collection primarily consists of material generated or collected in conjunction with Snow's unpublished manuscript, "The Camp on Campus: The Great War as Observed From a College Campus." The manuscript chronicles New York University's involvement with the military during World War I. Additional material includes twenty years of correspondence and memoranda collected in an effort to obtain material for the manuscript. Photographs illustrating various historical points made in the manuscript also are included.
Snow, Charles H., (Charles Henry), 1863-1957
Conditions Governing Access
Open for use without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into two series. Series I contains correspondence and memoranda Dean Snow collected in obtaining source material for his manuscript. Series II contains several different versions and revisions of the manuscript itself over a period of thirteen years.
Series I: Correspondence and Memoranda
Series II: "The Camp on Campus" (Manuscript)
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of materials collected by Charles H. Snow for his unpublished manuscript, "The Camp on Campus: The Great War as Observed From a College Campus." The majority of the materials are drafts of the manuscript itself, which chronicles New York University's involvement with the military during World War I. Additional material includes twenty years of correspondence and memoranda which Snow collected while conducting research for the manuscript. Photographs illustrating various historical points made in the manuscript are also included.
Series I includes original research material collected by Dr. Snow containing contemporary documentation from the World War I era. Also included is general correspondence ranging over eighteen years; some letters describes buildings and life on campus during the war years, and others relate to research and publication of the manuscript.
Included in Series II are many different versions of the manuscript preface, table of contents, eighteen chapters, appendices, and index. A 1943 note from Dr. Snow in Box 3, folder 6, details what the object of his manuscript was and why he decided not to publish it.
Biography of Charles H. Snow
Charles Henry Snow was born in New York City on March 24, 1863. He attended New York University's School of Civil Engineering and graduated in 1886. He received an honorary Sc.M. in 1894 and a Sc.D. in 1898 from the Western University of Pennsylvania (now the University of Pittsburgh). He joined NYU's Engineering faculty in 1891, and, in 1897, became Dean of the School of Civil Engineering.
In 1899 the name of the school was changed to the School of Applied Science (and was later changed to the College of Engineering). With Dean Snow at its helm, the school played a leading role during World War I, as NYU was one of the first universities to respond to President Woodrow Wilson's call for the training of engineering personnel. Dean Snow was the civilian director of the National Army Training Detachment (later Student Army Training Corps, Section B), where eleven hundred "Fighting Mechanics" were trained at NYU's campus at University Heights. As civilian director of these units, Dean Snow acted as liaison between the U.S. War Department and the University.
Dean Snow was author of The Principal Species of Wood, (1903, 1908); Wood and Other Organic Structure Materials, (1917); and several other papers in transactions with technical societies. He was also a member of New York City Mayor's Commission for National Defense, 1915-18; New York City Mayor's Committee of Citizens to arrange the Public Celebration of July Fourth, 1916-17; and a U.S. War Department appraisal expert, aircraft production, service at large, 1919.
Dean Snow served as Vice President of the New York University Senate from 1920 to 1931 and was named emeritus dean in 1930. He died October 29, 1957.
Custodial History
The papers of Charles H. Snow were presumably a part of a larger College of Engineering historical collection that covered the years 1897-1956. The collection was most likely accumulated at the University Heights Library over a period of approximately twenty years and was transferred to the University Archives when the School of Engineering closed in 1973.
Related Materials
Records of the Student Army Training Corps (1916-1921)
Administrative Papers of University College of Arts and Science, Office of the Dean (1899-1941)
Marshall Brown Collection on NYU Faculty and Students in World War I
Clinton Mindil Collection on NYU Alumni in World War I
Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-1968; New York University. College of Engineering.; New York University. School of Applied Science.; Correspondence.; Engineering |x Study and teaching; Influenza Epidemic |y 1918-1919 |z United States; Manuscripts for publication; Memorandums.; Military education |z United States |x History |y 20th century; New York University |x National Army Training Detachment |x History; New York University |x Reserve Officer Training Corps |x History; New York University |x Students.; New York University |x Students’ Army Training Corps |x History; New York University |x University College of Arts and Pure Science; Photographs.; Registers (lists).; United States |x War Department |x Committee on Education and Special Training; University Heights Church |z New York, N.Y.; World War |y 1914-1918 |x History; World War |y 1914-1918.
- Series I: Correspondence and Memoranda, 1917-1935
  Scope and Contents: Series I: Correspondence and Memoranda
  Included in Series I is original research material collected by Dr. Snow that contains a considerable amount of contemporary documentation from the World War I era. There are charts depicting the relationship between the National Army Training Detachment and the Student Army Training Corps (SATC) on the New York University Heights campus, a letter describing military training on the campus during the years 1917-1918, a list describing the nationality of some of the NYU staff dating to just before the U.S. entrance into World War I, a letter describing the relationship between the University Heights Church and the SATC, and a letter describing the commissary serving the SATC on the Heights campus. Also included is general correspondence ranging over eighteen years, with letters describing buildings and life on campus during the war years, a copy of a March 1922 letter asking for aid from a professor in Petrograd, comments on the manuscript by Professor Theodore F. Jones, and several letters from Dr. Snow to publishers. Among the memoranda, 1917-1935, are lists of men who left the campus for duty in 1917, notes on the influenza epidemic of 1918-1919, a memorandum on a Memorial Tablet for Alumni, Faculty, and Students who died in service during World War I, and a 1930 report from the Dean of the College of Engineering defending military instruction on campus and criticizing the University for not having yet published a list of students who served in the war.
  - Subseries A: Correspondence, 1917-1937
    - Chart: relationship between NATD and SATC, 1932 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General, 1921-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Military Training at University Heights, 1929 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nationality List, circa 1917, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - University Heights Church and SATC, 1926 December (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - War Commissary Experience, 1925 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries B: Memoranda, 1917-1935
    - General, 1917-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Report by Dean Snow, 1930 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: "The Camp on Campus" (Manuscript), 1930-1943
  Scope and Contents: Series II: "The Camp on Campus" (Manuscript)
  Included in Series II are many different versions of the preface, table of contents, eighteen chapters, appendices, and index; Box 3, folders 6 and 7 contain the manuscript's final draft. The first five chapters of the manuscript explain the historical setting of the United States from the turn of the century until its entrance into the war. Chapters six through seventeen describe the many ways the ensuing World War affected life on campus and chapter eighteen records the period of reconstruction and the resumption of a normal routine on campus. Included in Box 3, folder 6, is a note from Dr. Snow dated December 15, 1943, detailing what the object of his manuscript was and why he decided not to publish it.
  - Manuscript Fragments, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript Fragments, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Introduction - Chapter 18, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Introduction - Chapter 5, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chapter 6 - Chapter 12, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 13 - Chapter 17, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Introduction - Chapter 9, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 10 - Chapter 18, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Introduction - Chapter 6, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 7 - Chapter 12, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 13 - Chapter 18, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Index, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Introduction - Chapter 6, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 7 - Appendix, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Introduction, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Introduction - Chapter 8, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chapter 9 - Appendix, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bibliography, Suggested, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Index, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript Fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)